[Music]
let's let H sub K represent the harmonic
sum 1 plus a half plus a third up to one
over k
now consider a triangular array with n
minus one rows in the first row place
the harmonics on H1 in the second row
place the harmonic sum H2 and so on so
that the entry in row I and column J is
the fraction one over J
now consider a triangular array of boxes
with n rows take the number n and split
it into n copies of one then equally
distribute 1 into each column using
fractions so that column J contains all
entries of fractions one over J as
pictured
now for the trick we can combine these
two triangular arrays to make an N by n
Square
however if we now look at this Square
row by row we see that each row sums up
to the same value Row 1 is hn Row 2 is
hn and so on each row sums to the value
H sub n
but in this case there are n total rows
and therefore the sum of all the entries
is given by n times H sub n
but now we have an interesting identity
we see that if we sum up the harmonic
sums where K ranges from 1 to n minus 1
we have n times H sub n minus n
this is a formula for the sum of
harmonic sums but wait there's more that
we can do with this identity
we just proved visually that the sum of
harmonic sums where K ranges from 1 to n
minus 1 is equal to n times H sub n
minus n
we can get an equivalent identity by
adding H sub n to both sides
a theorem due to Ernesto Cesaro says
that if we have an infinite series that
converges with some s and we consider
the sequence of partial sums given by S
Sub n then the sequence of average
partial sums shown here also converges
to the same sum s
let's combine these two facts to prove
something interesting about the harmonic
series let's assume that the harmonic
series which is the sum where K ranges
from 1 to Infinity of the fractions 1
over K converges so that it has a sum s
this means that the limit as n
approaches Infinity of H sub n is equal
to s
then according to the theorem we have
that s is equal to the Limit as n
approaches Infinity of the average
partial sums but according to our
formula this limit can be replaced by
the limit as n approaches Infinity of H
sub n minus 1 plus h sub n over n and
this limit is equal to S minus 1 because
H sub n approaches s 1 approaches 1 and
N grows without bound
therefore we've proved that s equals s
minus 1.
but this is a contradiction and that
means that our assumption was incorrect
so that in fact the harmonic series
diverges